<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: yoga class planning | Yoga with Ivana]]></title>
  <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/categories/yoga-class-planning/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-06T00:55:52+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://yogawithivana.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ivana Miletic Demmel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Warrior Mum]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2013/09/05/warrior-mum/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-05T16:44:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2013/09/05/warrior-mum</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've been really enjoying teaching pregnancy yoga during my own pregnancy – sharing the practice with my lovely group of mums-to-be, going together through all the ups and downs of this fragile and powerful period of our lives and being inspired by each other. However, it gets a bit inconvenient when you become the most pregnant of all the students. Running around and trying to help everyone out with slight modifications of postures becomes quite a challenge. So, entering my 39th week, I've decided to start the maternity leave and resume teaching in November.</p>

<p>The last class for this season was dedicated to a theme I wanted to focus on for quite some time - Warrior Mum.</p>

<p>I love the warrior poses, with their strong grounded feet, the open heart and arms expanding powerfully up or to the sides. According to yoga every physical posture (asana) cultivates a certain attitude if performed regularly and with dedication, so flexibility of the body becomes flexibility of the mind. The warrior poses in this sense cultivate courage and open-heartedness, floating over the strong feet with wide open arms and giving hands. A beautiful metaphor for motherhood!</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/DancingWarrior.jpg" alt="Dancing Warrior asana"></img></p>


<p>Recently I came upon an interesting <a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/amy_cuddy_your_body_language_shapes_who_you_are.html">TED talk by Amy Cuddy</a>, a social psychologist from Harvard who doesn't have to do anything with yoga, but thinks that bodily postures we regularly assume shape the way we feel about ourselves and others. So, the poses of power, as she calls them, with legs comfortably apart and chest proudly forward, not only leave that impression on others, but can also boost our confidence and encourage us to develop such qualities in ourselves. Classical warrior would be a great example of a power pose in this sense.</p>

<p>The physical part of the class was focussed on energising flowing sequences based on and around the warrior poses. We started gradually preparing the body through loosening the spine, opening the hips and chest and strengthening the legs for a firmer grip in these powerful standing poses. I also found it useful to finish the class with more restorative poses releasing the tension in the lower back and hips.</p>

<p>Here are the little stick-men I drew planning this class:</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/PregnancyYogaClass22-Warrior_Mum_1.jpg" alt="Class plan page 1"></img></p>




<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/PregnancyYogaClass22-Warrior_Mum_2.jpg" alt="Class plan page 2"></img></p>




<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/PregnancyYogaClass22-Warrior_Mum_3.jpg" alt="Class plan page 3"></img></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Belly Dance Inspired Yoga]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2013/08/26/belly-dance-inspired-yoga/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-26T20:04:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2013/08/26/belly-dance-inspired-yoga</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Did you know that in many parts of the world they have special dances for pregnancy and birth, celebrating fertility, roundness and ripeness of the female body in pregnancy? This is how the oriental belly dance was "invented". It was a dance of pregnancy, dedicated to the moon as the feminine element. Heavily pregnant women would get together with their female cousins and just dance. Men would not even be allowed in there, it was a "women's thing". The soft circular and spiral movements of the belly and the whole body were used to keep the woman healthy and strong and get the baby in the optimal position for birth. They would give birth dancing, gently nudging the baby down the birth canal in soft round motions.</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/belly_dance_logo_by_contrapposto.jpg" alt="Belly dancer painting"></img></p>


<p>Photo credits: <a href="http://contrapposto.deviantart.com/art/Belly-Dance-Logo-69814644">Contrapposto</a></p>

<p>Inspired by the lovely lady at my recent <a href="http://www.activebirthcentre.com/">Active Birth workshop</a> who told me about the secret of belly dancing, I prepared a pregnancy yoga class based on oriental belly dance. The moves of belly dance are perfect for releasing tension in the hips, opening and energising the pelvic area and strengthening deep abdominal muscles. It was quite fun to let the hips roll experimenting with plenty of gentle round movements and I'm sure the little ones loved it too.</p>

<p>Researching and planning the class I've found out that there is already a couple of teachers, though mostly in the US and Australia who try to bring together yoga and belly dance. An interesting example is Australian based Lebanese-Palestinian <a href="http://www.bellydanceforbirth.com/flex/about_maha/47/1">Maha Al Musa</a>, a dancer, doula, writer and human rights activist, who gave birth to her last child at the age of 46 in her own home - belly dancing :) Here is one of her videos explaining the basic circular movement in belly dance.</p>

<iframe src="http://yogawithivana.com//www.youtube.com/embed/1kUkJ8_fm8w" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>Another lady who really knows how to spin her hips in the right way is Las Vegas based Amira, a belly dancer who released a DVD called <a href="http://www.pregnantbellydance.com/">Belly Dance and Yoga for Pregnancy</a>. The yoga part is very very basic and transitions between the poses sometimes quite rough, but the belly dancing part is awesome! It took me a while to decipher some of the hip loops. Later I realised that it's better to just let the hips get the movement before the mind.</p>

<p>Belly dance is not really an easy thing. In order to master it you need to learn how to move each segment of your body separately. I found it crazy how, for example, they can dance with the chest only while keeping the rest of the body still. So, only the part from the diaphragm to the neck moves, while the shoulders stay where they are. Or maybe moving just one hip in very tight circles... Huh, I guess these things are a bit out of reach for most of us in the West, used to use our hips in a bit...hm... more politically correct way.</p>

<p>Anyway, here are some of the little drawings I made during my research for the class, trying to understand the loops of hips drawing diagrams (oh, so Western from me).</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/BellyDanceResearch_HorizontalMoves.jpg" alt="Class research page 1"></img></p>




<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/BellyDanceResearch_UpperBodyMoves.jpg" alt="Class research page 2"></img></p>


<p>And here is the belly dance inspired yoga class we had (yeah, some more stick men :)</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/PregnancyYogaClass21-Belly_Dance_1.jpg" alt="Class plan page 1"></img></p>




<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/PregnancyYogaClass21-Belly_Dance_2.jpg" alt="Class plan page 2"></img></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Strength and Softness]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2013/08/11/strength-and-softness/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-11T13:44:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2013/08/11/strength-and-softness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The theme for this week's pregnancy yoga class was feminine strength and softness and childbirth as a perfect balance of the two.</p>

<p>For me personally, one of the most powerful motives from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yoga_Sutras_of_Patanjali">Yoga Sutras</a> is bringing together the opposites of constant efforts (abhyasa) and detachment (vayragya), finding a balance between being strong and letting go. In yoga we strive to find a way to reconcile these seemingly conflicting qualities so they could become one – understanding that a relaxed body is a strong body and a relaxed mind is a strong mind.</p>

<p>Applied to the birth, this means that strong muscles and a fit body are not enough to prepare you to go through the challenge of opening your body for the new life to emerge. Especially in the last part of pregnancy it's all about melting and softening, learning how to relax and go inwards, taking the mind out of the way of the body, allowing the cervix to soften and open. Besides cultivating the strength in ourselves we need to learn how to embrace our weakness too. Instead of fighting against pain you need to be able to dive into it, relax into it, letting go of any inhibitions, giving up your ego in hands of a force much more powerful than your own will – the force of nature.</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/overexposed.jpg" alt="Shadow play asana"></img></p>


<p>Photo credits: <a href="http://illuminate.uwenna.com/post/27628467620/shadow-play-asana">uwenna</a></p>

<p>Finding inspiration somewhere in between Yoga Sutras, Vinyasa Flow, Hypnobirthing relaxation techniques and Tantric visualisations, think I finally managed to strike the fragile balance between a restorative and enough physically challenging class to keep all my mums-to-be happy.</p>

<p>Since I have a very mixed group of expectant mums in different stages of pregnancy, with very different levels of previous experience with yoga, I've been experimenting with various ways to make the class suitable for each of them. So far I had the best experience with combining active segments with frequent short relaxation, either in one of the restorative poses (e.g. <a href="http://www.yogajournal.com/poses/475">child pose</a> and its variations), either in a form of active relaxation through slow and relaxing movements. In this class I've tried to go a step further and make the active segments shorter but more intense, interlacing them with guided relaxation, visualisations and deepening techniques, trying to reach a very deep level of relaxation in a short time. And it worked perfectly! All the mums-to-be were able to follow the class without any strain.</p>

<p>Here are some drawings I made planning the class:</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/PregnancyYoga19-Strength_Softness_1.jpg" alt="Class plan 1"></img></p>




<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/PregnancyYoga19-Strength_Softness_2.jpg" alt="Class plan 2"></img></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
