<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Yoga with Ivana]]></title>
  <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-09-15T23:25:23+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://yogawithivana.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ivana Miletic Demmel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Buddhist Networking]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2016/04/01/Metta-Networking/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-01T10:03:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2016/04/01/Metta-Networking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/hands-together.jpg" alt="photo of hands holding firmly together"></img></p>


<p>Last night I went to a really cool workshop called “Networking for people who don’t like networking” with <a href="https://twitter.com/Tazeenahmad">Tazeen Ahmad</a>, famous by writing about introversion as power and working with introverted leaders. My lovely husband got me a voucher for <a href="http://www.theschooloflife.com/london/">The School of Life</a> and this looked way too interesting to miss. And besides, I was never a big networker to start with and was curious to find out what could be done to improve that.</p>

<p>On the way there I was reading <a href="http://ajahnsucitto.org/">Ajahn Sucitto’s Parami</a> on the tube — maybe my favourite book about meditation so far, which happens not to be about meditation at all. Each page is just precious and I keep reading it at a snail pace, allowing every single drop to sink in. Serendipitously, this time I came upon a chapter about metta — the Buddhist practice of loving kindness. It’s beautiful how that set a completely different stage for my experience of this whole evening filled with networking — a thing I would usually find a bit awkward and overwhelming.</p>

<p>The main issue for the mind is how it relates to what happens — Ajahn Succito writes. The mind sees the world and gets an idea that what it sees is “out there” and separate from it. Every act of perceiving the world through seeing / hearing / touching needs a subject — who is perceiving and an object — that what is being perceived. Out of this duality a sense of self and other arises. These are relative positions and depending on each other — a subject can’t exist without an object which is in contrast to it and an object needs a subject to experience it . But this is a functional distinction and not set in stone. The subject is still part of the world that it is seeing / hearing / touching and not out of it — we belong to the world and it belongs to us. </p>

<p>The problem is that we are basing our whole identity on this sense of self and other— ourselves as being distinct and independent from the world that we are a part of. And this creates a sense of separation and alienation.</p>

<p>Metta means softening this sense of separation. Practising loving kindness we look into the mind, moment by moment with an intention to gentle it out of the hold of aversion and anxiety — Ajahn Sucitto says. The sense of self and other can also provide ground for an intention to offer support. To give. And this is what connects us instead of separating us from others.</p>

<p>After reading about metta and spending this enriching evening with Tazeen, it finally made sense to me that networking could mean applying metta to professional relationships — connecting at a very human level.</p>

<p>Making contacts is about giving, offering yourself to others. It’s not about selling yourself and your skills, but offering genuine support — ‘What can I give you?’ instead of ‘What can I get from you?’ And this completely shifts the perspective — we are all playing for for the same team.</p>

<p>If you are shy, sensitive or an introvert there is a lot you can give to others as a great listener, for example. Instead of trying to approach people and win them over with your amazing professional skills and individual qualities, maybe you can simply be curious about people and eager to find out more about them and how you can help each other. </p>

<p>Every person has a unique story. Listening is an opportunity to be moved and inspired, to learn from others and ourselves — allowing stories to unfold.</p>

<p>The trick is shifting the focus from “myself” to a situation — not thinking how you can use it, but how you can make yourself useful in the given context.</p>

<p>Metta is about recognising otherness and feeling that it’s OK. Not being confronted by it. Not judging others or ourselves based on others. Cultivating a mind of goodwill, kindness and support.</p>

<p>This article was also published on <a href="https://medium.com/@zzuuu/">Medium</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving yourself stronger]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2016/02/21/Moving-yourself-stronger/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-21T12:47:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2016/02/21/Moving-yourself-stronger</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>More time I spend learning about the body more I wonder: do we really need “core strengthening” to make us stronger? We might be trying to solve a wrong problem, blaming everything on “the core” as some powerful source of strength inside the body that we need to train and strengthen in isolation from everything else.</p>

<p>It’s interesting how the approach to abdominal exercises has been changing in last couple of decades — from the military-style crunches in 1980-es with the lower back pushed into the floor, to keeping the small curve in the lower back in 1990-es. And then in late 1990-es the whole concept of “core” came up and everyone got obsessed with transversus abdominis (TrA) and pulling the navel in like pressing a magic button of stability and strength.</p>

<p>A couple of weeks ago I came upon <a href="http://www.cpdo.net/Lederman_The_myth_of_core_stability.pdf">an intriguing article by Prof. Eyal Lederman</a> that added some more oil to the fire of my doubt pointing to quite a bit of research that could shake the grounds of the widely-accepted idea of “core stability” training and its efficiency.</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/moving-male-figures.jpg" alt="drawing of moving male figures"></img></a></p>




<h2>The idea of “core” and its training is a reductionist fantasy based on arbitrary assumptions—Lederman says.</h2>


<p>The concept of “core stability” emerged out of a research showing a change in onset timing of the muscles of the torso in patients with back injuries and chronic back pain. But then, combined with the Pilates idea of strong abdominals as a base of strength, it stretched to involve a couple of arbitrary assumptions. First, that there is a separate group of “core muscles” that works independently from the rest of the body and that we can train in isolation. Second, that training the “core” can help cure back pain and prevent injury.</p>

<p>Lederman points at a couple of different studies conducted on pregnant and postpartum women that show that there is not necessarily a link between weak abdominals and back pain. He challenges the key role of TrA in stabilising the torso and questions the widely-spread idea that training TrA can help with back pain or reduce the recurrence of back pain.</p>

<p>But what I found the most interesting, was deconstructing the myth of muscle timing training, which is the base of “core stability”. <strong>We are talking about one fiftieth of a second</strong> difference in muscle activation in case of people with back injuries comparing to healthy subjects. These timings are well beyond the patient’s conscious control and the clinical capabilities of the therapist to test or alter — he says. Even if we could effectively re-train muscle timings, that would mean interfering with a complex mechanism that our bodies use to protect us from further injury.</p>

<p>You could go around the timing problem by activating TrA all the time. But this way you use a force that is often more than what you need to efficiently perform a task, unnecessarily compressing the lumbar spine. Also tensing of the abdominal muscles increases intra-abdominal pressure which in some cases (e.g pelvic girdle pain) can cause further damage to pelvic ligaments.</p>

<h2>Trying to override the body’s defence mechanism developed through thousands of years of evolution by pulling the navel in is not only energy inefficient, but can even lead to injury.</h2>


<p>Another thing which really resonated with me, was examining the “core stability” approach from the aspect of similarity principle in learning of motor skills. <strong>“We can’t learn to play the piano by practicing the banjo”</strong> — Lederman says. If you learn to activate TrA while lying on your back, there is no guarantee that this would transfer to control and physical adaptation during standing, sitting, bending, lifting, running.</p>

<p>Which basically means, the only way to strengthen the body to be able to respond to various positions is to use it in all of these. Or in other words — to MOVE.</p>

<p>Which made me think, our hunter-gatherer ancestors never went to a gym and probably never ever thought of doing any core strengthening and still had enough core strength to survive in wilderness hunting their lunch. But the thing is, they moved — all day, every day, more in summer, less in winter, but at least a couple of miles every day. They climbed trees, carried their children, sat on the ground to prepare their food and eat. And none of them ever even heard of core stability.</p>

<p>Our modern weak core epidemic, sort of, is a response to the way we live and use our bodies day to day — driving everywhere, spending most time sitting on couches and comfortable chairs. There is rarely any need to use your strength, unless maybe sometimes carrying a suitcase up the stairs when the lift is out of order or occasionally moving a piece of furniture. And then you throw your back out.</p>

<p>We need to think out of “the core” to fix the core — Katy Bowman, biomechanicist and founder of <a href="https://nutritiousmovement.com/">Nutritious Movement™</a> says. Can 3–5 hours in the gym offset the rest of the week spent sitting, pretty much in one position every day from nine to five?</p>

<h2>The same as what we eat shapes us, the way we move over time shapes us too. Not just exercise, but every movement and lack there of counts.</h2>


<p>Our bodies have adapted to very limited use and repetitive positioning of the joints throughout the day. As some of our hardly used joints stiffen and whole areas of the body clump together, unable to move independently, the joints that still DO move have to bear all of the strain for the ones that don’t. And this is the body we bring into the gym and “challenge”, pretty much asking for injury.</p>

<h2>It’s often not strength that is the problem, but mobility.</h2>


<p>‘You’ll often find that “hard moves” you thought you weren’t strong enough to do were actually hard because your body wasn’t mobile enough to capitalise on the geometry that makes them doable.’ — Bowman says. Through using the body more and in more ways, we can restore mobility in the stiff areas and allow muscles to do their job in stabilising the body as we move.</p>

<p>Your “core” works in respond to every movement of the body, and the lack of movement. No matter what kind of a “core strengthening” programme you might use, if you don’t move that much or that well your “core” will continue being weak.</p>

<p>We need to bring movement back into the way we live, bit by bit. Not only in the gym. Not only to “challenge” ourselves after a whole day or even weeks and months of not moving. Exercises are useful, but they just can’t work in isolation. It’s what we do all day that counts.</p>

<p>Bowman makes a parallel between movement and nutrition in which exercises are an equivalent of vitamins — useful as a supplement only, but not able to replace eating well altogether.</p>

<h2>A healthy movement diet looks something like this:</h2>

<ul>
<li>Walking, walking , walking</li>
<li>Squatting and sitting on the floor</li>
<li>Lifting and carrying</li>
<li>Hanging and climbing</li>
</ul>


<p>So the same as we make effort to eat our 5 servings of fruits and veggies per day, we need to make sure to squeeze in at least a bit of each of these types of movements in our day as the main source of our movement nutrients.</p>

<p>The body stabilises itself in response to movement. It’s all about proprioception — sensing and responding to the environment as we move. Our feet and hands behave as sensory organs giving us information through a level of joint distortion. And even looking deeper into the body — our muscles not just execute the movement but also react to the sensory input of the environment, tensing and releasing when needed.</p>

<h2>There is no need to “engage your core” to stabilise the spine. If you need to make an effort to activate your “core” squeezing and forcing, it probably means that either your muscles are not sensing the load or the load is more than your current strength.</h2>


<p>And this is basically the same view I found in work of <a href="http://www.somatics.de/Godard/ReadingBodyInDance.pdf">dance educator Hubert Godard</a> — there is no need to keep the tension in the centre but allow the body to respond freely to movement, gliding fluidly between the earth and the sky.
So my point is: maybe it’s time to stop worrying about “the core” and make space for more movement in our lives.</p>

<p>Walk, squat, use your arms more and in more ways, climb a tree if you can. No exercise programme can strengthen a body which is not being used otherwise. It’s only a healthy variety of movement that can keep your joints supple and your muscles at optimal length to be able to generate force.</p>

<p>And release the belly — instead of keeping it pulled in all the time, leaving space for the body to stabilise itself as and when needed. <strong>A relaxed and responsive body is a strong body.
</strong></p>

<p>This article was also published on <a href="https://medium.com/@zzuuu/">Medium</a></p>

<p>Reference list:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Eyal Lederman — The Myth of Core Stability, Journal of Bodywork and Movement Therapies Volume 14, Issue 1, January 2010, p. 84–98</p></li>
<li><p>Katy Bowman, MA — Move Your DNA: Restore Your Health Through Natural Movement, Propriometrics Press, September 25th 2014</p></li>
<li><p>Radebold, A., et al. — Muscle response pattern to sudden trunk loading in healthy individuals and in patients with chronic low back pain, Spine, 2000, 25(8): p. 947–54.</p></li>
<li><p>Helewa, A., et al. — Does strengthening the abdominal muscles prevent low back pain — a randomized controlled trial, J Rheumatol, 1999. 26(8): p. 1808–15</p></li>
<li><p>Katy Bowman, MA — Diastasis Recti : The Whole Body Solution to Abdominal Weakness and Separation, Propriometrics Press, January 2016</p></li>
<li><p>Hubert Godard — Reading The Body in Dance http://www.somatics.de/Godard/ReadingBodyInDance.pdf</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[In praise of slow]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2015/12/24/in-praise-of-slow/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-24T22:17:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2015/12/24/in-praise-of-slow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/sloths.jpg" alt="illustration of sloths"></img></p>


<p>illustration by <a href="http://www.lindsaydaleart.com/">Lindsay Dale</a></p>

<p>Some call sloths <em>the bodhisattva of the forest</em> because they have an inherent peaceful smile on their faces while hanging in the trees. This unique animal has evolved in direction of slowness instead of speed - their slowness is their survival strategy. Sloths have a very slow metabolism and little food keeps them going for days. They have very little muscle mass and are light enough to rest hanging from thin branches in the very tops of the trees where predators can hardly reach them.</p>

<p>According to Japanese anthropologist and environmental activist <a href="http://www.sloth.gr.jp/tsuji/koiwa.html">Keibo Oiwa</a> slowness is a beautiful skill we can learn from sloths. &#8216;Slow is beautiful’ he says. &#8216;In the modern world you have to go faster, so that the other person feels that he or she has to go faster too. Then you have to go faster again. We are actually stealing time from each other. After all, time is the only thing that belongs to us in this life. Life is time. We have been trying to be successful in this competitive world by sacrificing the only thing we have, which is time.’</p>

<p>But we can also reclaim and appreciate our time. We can embrace slowness.</p>

<p>Have a beautifully slow Christmas all!</p>

<p>Big thanks to <a href="http://www.resurgence.org/magazine/article4485-slow-small-and-simple.html">Resurgence Magazine</a> for sharing this inspiring story!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unfolding]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2015/11/30/unfolding/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-30T09:17:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2015/11/30/unfolding</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/the-leaf-copy.jpeg"></img></a></p>


<p>Simply open your fingers</br>
Let the squashed little bird</br>
With ruffled feathers</br>
Fly out of your palm</br>
</br>
No need for clenching</br>
Just soften, release the fists</br>
We are not here to defeat the world</br>
But offer ourselves as a gift</br>
</br>
Open your hands with courage</br>
The whole universe pulsates</br>
In each of your trembling fingers</br>
Fragile and eager</br>
</br>
Just open to wonder</br>
Allow the tender petals to unfold</br>
And bloom effortlessly</br>
Through your fingertips</br></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why not to 'tuck the tailbone' in a yoga class]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2015/11/18/finding-a-more-pelvic-floor-friendly-yoga-practice/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-18T14:07:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2015/11/18/finding-a-more-pelvic-floor-friendly-yoga-practice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>A couple of ideas on having a more pelvic-floor-friendly yoga practice</em></p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/yoga-drawing.jpg" alt="drawing of bodies in various yoga poses"></img></p>


<p>It is quite common to hear yoga teachers saying ‘tuck the tailbone under’ when they want to initiate action from the ‘core’ (mulabandha). This might be useful in some cases, working with beginners and people who don’t have much awareness of their pelvic floor and the action of tucking the tail can help them access the muscles their brain doesn’t ‘talk to’. But this hint is used way too much and often unnecessarily. Some yoga styles even encourage keeping the tailbone tucked under in most poses for ‘stability’.</p>

<p>The problem is, ‘tuck the tailbone’ could be:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><em>Misleading</em> — Pelvic floor lift in yoga (mulabandha) should come from toning and lifting at the central tendon of the pelvic floor (between the openings) and not from the action of the tailbone. Telling students to tuck the tailbone makes them over-activate wrong muscles — gripping the gluteals, tightening the hamstrings, the deep hip rotators and the very back of the pelvic floor, without lifting the central tendon.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Exposing you to injury</em> — When you tuck the tailbone under trying to stabilise the body, tightening your gluteals and the hips together with the rectus abdominis flattens the lower back. This interferes with the stabilising action of the transversus abdominis (TVA) in front and the lumbar multifidus muscles in the back. <a href="http://alinenewton.com/pdf-articles/core.htm">The multifidi can’t work properly when the back is flat.</a> <em>This is why a lot of people end up with back pain after classes that focus on ‘core strength’.</em></p></li>
<li><p><em>Bad for your pelvic floor</em> — keeping the tailbone under we decrease the space between the pubic bone and the tailbone i.e. shorten the pelvic floor. Continuously contracting the pelvic floor while keeping it short <a href="http://mamasweat.blogspot.co.uk/2010/05/pelvic-floor-party-kegels-are-not.html">will pull the sacrum into the bowl of the pelvis causing your pelvic floor to slack.</a> Doing more ‘strengthening’ work with your tail tucked under will make your pelvic floor even shorter and tighter, but not stronger. Unlike the TVA that (as a purely stabilising muscle) can work for longer periods of time, <a href="http://www.somatics.de/Godard/ReadingBodyInDance.pdf">the pelvic floor should activate only when we need an extra burst of energy</a> and then release to its full length. ‘Keeping it lifted’ = pelvic floor disorders in a long term.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>A more pelvic-floor-friendly way to perform mulabandha, would be to <strong>keep the pelvis in a neutral position</strong> and try to initiate the lift from midway in between the openings without tucking the tailbone.</p>

<p><em>Keeping the tail untucked we can strengthen and lengthen muscles of the pelvic floor (eccentric contraction) instead of shortening them (concentric contraction).</em></p>

<p>To be able to identify the right muscle, instead of focusing on action of the tailbone I find it useful to <strong>pay attention to action of sitbones</strong>, which with the lift of the pelvic floor come closer and with the release slide apart.</p>

<p>There is no need to actively squeeze the sphincters, but just allow the area midway between the openings to gently lift up. I usually say ‘<strong>lift from the base of the torso</strong>’. This way we can promote the toning action of the pelvic floor, without overdoing it.</p>

<p>The next step could be to use mulabandha only as an exception and instead focus on stabilising the torso from front and back — organically activating TVA and lumbar multifidus muscles as we move. An extra lift from the pelvic floor could be added only when needed to ‘energise the movement’. Dance educator Hubert Godard uses this model to promote a fluid, responsive stability in movement, as opposed to keeping tension in the centre of the body. This could be beautifully applied to the postural practice of yoga too.</p>

<p><em>We can use use the pelvic lift only as an exception and instead focus on stabilising the torso organically from front and back, keeping fluidity and freedom of movement.</em></p>

<p>TVA naturally activates as you use <strong>Ujjayi breath</strong>. Or you can consciously activate it, especially in case of people with lower back injuries or weak abdominals. I like to use ‘<strong>draw the hip points towards each other</strong>’ to help my students find TVA. <a href="http://www.doyoga.com/resources.html">Doug Keller</a> uses a nice hint here, saying ‘imagine pulling the drawstring on a pair of sweatpants tighter’. If you on top of it say ‘<strong>keep your pelvis neutral</strong>’, you can make sure that the lumbar multifidus muscles which protect the discs in the lower back automatically co-contract with TVA completely stabilising the torso.</p>

<p><em>Your ‘core’ works fully when the spine is in a neutral position.</em></p>

<p>Having the spine in a neutral position is different for every person, but it basically means maintaining the natural curves of the spine while having <a href="https://theverticalworkshop.wordpress.com/2011/04/01/neutral-pelvis-and-neutral-spine-what-are-they-and-why-do-we-care/">the pelvis in a neutral position</a>. This way both deep abdominal muscles (TVA) and the deep muscles along the spine (lumbar multifidus) are working to their optimum — balancing the spine and providing enough stability for each movement.</p>

<p>If you go into a backbend, you get support mostly from the front (TVA) which gradually weakens deeper you arch the lower back. And then again, if you tuck the tailbone under scooping the pelvis and flattening the lower back, the multifidus muscles can’t activate to stabilise from the back. Of course you should move freely in your postural practice, but still be aware that deeper you go to each extreme in moving the pelvis and the lumbar spine, less stability you have and more you are exposed to injuries.</p>

<p>I personally try to avoid tucking the tailbone hint even in case of working with people who have difficulty in activating their pelvic floor and deep abdominal muscles (e.g. after childbirth). Instead of using action of the tailbone to help in developing awareness of the ‘undercarriage’ I find it useful to make them squeeze a block or a small ball with the thighs while trying to gently tone the lower belly, just above the pubic bone, keeping the pelvis in a neutral position.</p>

<p>Please don’t take me wrong, tucking the tailbone is not bad in itself and please by all means do it as a part of your varied movement diet! But there is really no need to use it as default when practising yoga or living our lives.</p>

<p>This post was also published on <a href="https://medium.com/@zzuuu/why-not-to-tuck-the-tailbone-in-a-yoga-class-d088c5592066#.jwgczqdkv">Medium</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Space to grow into]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2015/11/14/space-to-grow-into-healthy-alignment-anatomy/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-14T08:06:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2015/11/14/space-to-grow-into-healthy-alignment-anatomy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been just watching <a href="http://anatomytrains.co.uk/?wpsc-product=bodyreading-101-visual-assessment">Tom Myers’s DVD training in bodyreadying</a> Have never really seen anyone explain the postural tilts and shifts so beautifully. Have never really seen anyone explain the postural tilts and shifts so beautifully.</p>

<p>Another thing I really liked is that he doesn’t just readjust the body as it ‘should be’ but explores where to get that extra little space for expansion.
In order to make an alignment shift sustainable, we need to focus on the body as a whole, looking not only for the areas of the body that have been overused and start to trouble us, but also the underused ones. We need to find an individual’s capacity to expand.</p>

<p>I’ve found my own extra little space upwards, discovering the simplicity and ease of rebounding from the earth and lengthening up through yoga. And I literally grew some 2–2.5 cm taller though already in my early thirties. The spine realigned itself, slightly decreasing its excessive curvature and getting some more length.</p>

<p>Our bodies are beautifully plastic and can adapt to our lifestyles and compensate for our postural habits in a variety of ways. Similarly they can gradually adopt a better alignment if we offer them space for expansion through movement, the space to grow into.</p>

<p>This makes me think of Chinese gardens. As opposed to Western tightly trimmed grass and perfectly symmetrical lanes of flowers, they focus on wild beauty of nature, creating the effect that ‘although made by mankind, it seemed created by God’. They don’t try to tame nature but work together with it, making space in which nature can grow of its own accord.</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/bamboo-garden.jpg" alt="photo of a bamboo garden"></img></a></p>


<p>We need to work together with the body and allow it to find a sustainable solution in realigning itself, rather than force it into a particular ‘healthy’ alignment. It’s not enough to consciously drop the ribs, untuck the pelvis, check yourself in the mirror and just keep checking if you are in alignment thousand times a day. The change needs to happen at subconscious level. As we make space for the body to realign itself, the change will feel natural and won’t need to be consciously maintained. The body will grow into a healthy alignment — in its own way, gradually finding its new normal.</p>

<p>This post was also published on <a href="https://medium.com/@zzuuu/space-to-grow-into-1ab0ba4fc37b#.aycoi6cea">Medium</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The forgotten art of untucking the tail]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2015/11/07/squats-pregnancy-birth-pelvic-floor/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-07T18:41:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2015/11/07/squats-pregnancy-birth-pelvic-floor</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/squat-illustration.png" alt="squat illustration"></img></a></p>


<p>I’ve been spending most of my time lately learning about biomechanics, healthy alignment and how movement affects our bodies in relation to gravity. The research from the last couple of years shows that the way we move affect us not only mechanically, as it was previously thought, but also causing biochemical changes on cellular level, changing us from inside out. This process of the body adapting to and being shaped by movement is called mechanotransduction.</p>

<p>We seem to be living in the world that encourages sitting with the tail tucked under. The furniture we use sitting all day is optimised for comfort and convenience, but usually not ergonomically adapted for pelvic floor health. Who would even think about that? There is a well spread myth in our society that pelvic floor issues are a normal consequence of pregnancy and birth, or ageing for men. But we would rarely think of looking for a cause a bit deeper, in the way we have been living and moving before that.</p>

<p>Did you know that the anatomic function of our remnant of a tail is, amongst others, to control opening and closing of the pelvic outlet. If you look at a dog, or a another tailed animal, you can see that they keep their tail up, happily wagging when they are in a good mood. And this is the default. When you see a dog wearing his tail down between his back legs, it is usually a sign that the dog is on the fight of flight mode and his pelvic floor is tense as a part of his whole body reacting to danger.</p>

<p>Even though we now have only the beginning of what was once a real mammalian tail, it behaves the same. Untucking the tailbone opens the pelvic outlet, tucking it closes it - tightening the pelvic floor. The dog with his tail down between his legs is an equivalent of you sitting on your sacrum, the back supported by a chair or a couch. If you spend multiple hours a day in this position, your pelvic floor doesn’t really have a chance to release and allow the muscle fibres to regain their natural length at resting state. So gradually it shortens.</p>

<p>In his book Pelvic Power, <a href="http://franklinmethod.com/">Eric Franklin</a> compares natural movement of the pelvic floor to a kite. As you stand up the pelvic floor slightly lifts and narrows similarly to a kite picking the wind and taking off. Reversely, as you sit down (with untucked tail, using your sitbones) the pelvic floor widens and releases to its full length, like a kite descending down, opening and landing. But what if we never allow it to release?</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/kites_web.jpg" alt="kite flying"></img></a></p>


<p>Biomechanicist <a href="http://www.katysays.com/category/pelvic-floor-stuffs/">Katy Bowman</a> compares an optimally functioning pelvic floor to a trampoline. It supports the weight of all our pelvic organs and allows any extra load to just bounce off its healthy, elastic fibres, tensing and releasing naturally. Keeping the muscles short all the time doesn’t let them perform their function optimally. And further on, as our bodies naturally adapt to the way we use them, we gradually end up with shortened muscles.</p>

<p>This is further exacerbated by using pelvic floor exercises (‘Kegels’) on ‘the more the better’ basis - Bowman explains. Doing more and more repetitions of contractions of the muscle isolated from the rest of the body without allowing it to ever fully release, you get a muscle that is tight and locked short. Tight muscle does NOT equal a strong muscle. A strong muscle is able to both fully contract and fully release.</p>

<p>So why I am telling you all this now? Reading Katy Bowman’s last book - <a href="http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/21988559-move-your-dna">Move Your DNA</a>, I’ve started to incorporate more movement into my life other than and independently from exercising. And especially, I’ve started to squat more, when playing with my toddler, picking things off the floor and even going to the toilet.</p>

<p>Learning to untuck my tail has made me finally realise why I still had to push my baby out and not bear it gently down, letting the gravity do the job, in spite of all the birth preparations and beautiful relaxation techniques I mastered beforehand. To &#8220;breathe the baby out&#8221; you have to first untuck your tail.</p>

<p>Anatomically, in order for the baby to come out the pelvic floor has to release, but you can’t possibly release the pelvic floor with the tailbone tucked under. You can only use the strength of your muscles (transverse abdominals and diaphragm as they instruct you to hold your breath and “puuuuussssh!”) against your pelvic floor. And that’s a sure way to end up with a nice tear and possibly a pelvic floor disfunction. I was lucky that the athletic challenge, how my birth experience felt to be honest, ended without a severe damage. My body just took over at the last moment and following a very primal instinct jumped on a dining chair opening the pelvic outlet fully. The squats and kneeling with rounded back would have probably taken me to an assisted delivery.</p>

<p>&#8220;Modern birthing science has placed a large burden on secreted hormones (like relaxin) to prepare the body for needed mobility.&#8221; Katy Bowman says. Yes, hormon relaxine is useful in letting the body open up for the birth, but it’s not enough, unless we have strong muscles that can fully contract, but also fully release. But then, strong isolated muscles are not enough either. In order to have smooth births we ned to have a whole-body endurance. A great way to develop endurance is to walk as much as you can. &#8220;The woman who wants to go about a birthing process naturally can follow the lead other “natural” processes women have been doing for millennia – walking 5-6 total miles per day, and squatting to bathroom multiple times daily.&#8221; - she adds.</p>

<p>So, the bottom line is: untuck the tail. Walk more and move more, in general and especially when pregnant. Making even tiny adjustments towards moving more and moving better we can give our bodies a chance to function up to their very best.</p>

<hr />

<p>This post was also published on <a href="https://medium.com/@zzuuu/the-forgotten-art-of-untucking-the-tail-57d8ef619e4e#.y7x5dy876">Medium</a> and to my shock seen by around 340 thousand people. This has made me realise the importance of pelvic health and has pulled me deeper into learning about pelvic floor and pelvic girdle health as an important aspect of our wellbeing. Looking forward to be sharing with you as I learn and explore more!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[About yoga and poetry - becoming infinitely small]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2015/04/05/about-yoga-and-poetry-becoming-infinitely-small/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-05T16:11:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2015/04/05/about-yoga-and-poetry-becoming-infinitely-small</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I stumbled upon a dazzling quote of Roberto Bolaño <em>&#8220;In poetry, you become infinitely small without disappearing.”</em> And it reminded me how much I miss writing poems and that feeling of standing on the edge of unknown and leaving your self behind as you jump in.</p>

<p>It’s been a while since I wrote anything so beautifully flowing and irrational that you can dare call it poetry. Starting with a vague idea, or not even that, just following a familiar tickle in my fingers, grabbing a pen and seeing where it all goes. Scribbling on napkins in cafes and back of public transport tickets. Writing as an exploration, listening carefully to the ripples of the deep, instinctive mind and trying to mirror it in words. Letting the story smoothly thread itself through my fingers.</p>

<p>Funny… I realised this morning teaching a small class that it’s this same feeling I sometimes have while teaching yoga - stepping on the mat without any idea what is going to happen, letting the class unfold gently by itself, simply diving in. Of course, when you realise there are for example too many hip openers, it’s useful to let the rational mind jump in with a counter sequence to balance it out. But sometimes the class can unfold itself effortlessly, without the need for much interference and you as a teacher can simply step back and allow yourself to become infinitely small. One of my great inspirations, Malaysian yoga teacher <a href="https://mengfoonglai.wordpress.com/">Meng Foong</a> beautifully explains it: &#8220;There is nobody. No students. No you… Just yoga.&#8221;</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><a href="http://amandacass.vc.net.nz/">
<img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/flying.jpg" alt="a drawing of a girl flying with dandelion flowers like balloons"></img></a></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why go to India to study yoga?]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2015/03/05/why-go-to-India-to-study-yoga/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-05T14:35:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2015/03/05/why-go-to-India-to-study-yoga</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/santacruz-market.jpg" alt="a busy Indian market"></img></p>


<p>An old friend got in touch the other day asking for my opinion about two different yoga teacher courses in India. Both were obviously targeted at the Western audience, being quite daringly priced for Indian standards. Do you think they are genuine? - he asked. They both seem to be accredited by American Yoga Alliance.</p>

<p>No, I don’t think they are a fraud, I wrote. They do exist, have a website, and probably do train people from all over the world in a set of skills we conventionally expect from a yoga teacher. But the question of authenticity is something different. It all depends on what exactly you are looking for, I guess. Why is that you are going to India in the first place? What is that you are seeking? Is it a specific set of skills, accreditation, an experience or maybe something different?</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/peeking-out.jpg" alt="a view from an Indian rickshaw"></img></p>


<p>The two courses he sent seemed to be similar to a number of courses available in the UK, even the prices were pretty much the same. They offer an internationally recognised 200 hour accreditation and a curriculum focussing on asanas and other concrete techniques, even learning how to run your yoga business. They seemed perfect for someone who wants to spend a couple of weeks away, in a warm, tropical setting mastering their headstand and a couple of other advanced postures and come back with a title of a yoga teacher, ready to get their business off the ground.</p>

<p>Please don’t take me wrong, that is a completely viable reason to do a yoga teacher training. We all need to live of something. And it’s definitely nicer if you want to make teaching yoga your profession - making people healthier and happier instead of doing something that supports the system you personally don’t believe in.</p>

<p>Being able to earn more money from teaching yoga is also fine. If that is your aim, that is completely understandable. But do you really need to go to India for that? Maybe you can do it a whole lot cheaper somewhere in Europe? At least the flight wouldn’t be that expensive.</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/laundry.jpg" alt="rows of drying laundry in a Mumbai slum"></img></p>


<h3>Maybe we need a cultural shock to really experience what it means to live yoga.</h3>

<p>For me personally, the highest value of studying yoga in India was being pushed out of my comfort zone and getting a chance to take a look at my whole value system afresh. Maybe we need to leave our cosy world for a moment to be able to truly understand the cultural and religious context in which yoga was born and really experience the modest and disciplined way of life that yoga traditionally meant. And this definitely doesn’t have much in common with detox green juices and perfect bodies in branded yoga pants posing in graceful, breathtaking backbends, which in a way was my perception of yoga-lifestyle before that.</p>

<h3>Your diarrhoea, allergy to mosquito bites or the fact that you don’t like okra don’t make any difference in a big picture. You are small and unimportant…</h3>

<p>Staying at a modest, traditionally organised ashram without fancy facilities and many foreign students, you might not experience 5 star comfort, but will for sure get exposed to a life different enough to permanently change you. Being immersed into a completely different, sometimes overwhelming world with values often intimidating at first sight, you get a chance to step back from our common self-centred way of seeing the world and take a look at a larger picture for a moment. You are just a tiny wheel in a larger process of life. Your diarrhoea, allergy to mosquito bites or the fact that you don’t like okra don’t make any difference. You are small and unimportant… and that is so beautifully empowering. Now you are probably wondering: what the heck is she talking about? Well, I’ll try to explain, please do read further!</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/yoga-mudra.jpg" alt="a bowing yoga practitioner in an Indian yoga school"></img></p>


<h3>Encounter with the ego: going beyond yourself</h3>

<p>Some concepts of yogic philosophy are totally alien to our Western logic and using solely your intellect to get around them doesn’t make much sense. For example, the concept of dharma from Bhagavad Gita, often translated to English as duty, at first sounds like a bold denial of free will. Hm… Coming from the West, freedom is what for most of us yoga is all about and why we are “in the game” to start with. However, diving deeper into the whole value system of Bhagavad Gita you come to experience that this duty is not a chore, not a denial of freedom, but something that comes as a fulfilment, finding your own innate purpose - acting from the full depth of your being.</p>

<p>It’s a similar story with the concept of karma yoga, the term often used in the West to justify teaching yoga for free and other work without remuneration. Karma yoga is not about cutting the goal out of the picture (in this case fair payment for the service), but totally shifting the focus from goal to process itself. We come to experience selfless work as going beyond yourself through action, transcending the limits of the ego. The process sets itself free from the result and becomes the fulfilment. And work, another concept seen as a chore in our perspective, becomes a path to enlightenment and true liberation.</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/work.jpg" alt="traditional drawing of working people"></img></p>


<p>And there is a whole lot of other examples - like tapa (austerity, discipline), swadhyaya (self-study), Iswara pranidhana (surrendering to the higher self, in a way), or unconditional love. We do need a cultural shock and a short upside-down of our whole value system to be able to truly experience them. But do you really want that? I guess it all depends again on what you are looking for and how deep into the rabbit hole you are willing to dive. And do you even want to change?</p>

<h3>Living, breathing, drinking and eating yoga</h3>

<p>Although India today is largely affected by globalisation and especially richer people have a life quite similar to people of upper middle and high class Westerners, it’s still possible to find hidden pockets of spirituality free of materialism and materialist spiritualism.</p>

<p>If you are after something like this, maybe a good place to check would be modest local yoga institutes with ashrams. They are run as non-profit organisations and often kept in the same family for generations, being able to trace their roots back to their original guru. Institutes&#8217; work is aimed mostly at Indian students, trying to preserve yoga as a tradition and a system of values - living, breathing, drinking and eating yoga. They see yoga as a spiritual path and simply a way of being, loving and selflessly serving others.</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/classroom.jpg" alt="the yoga institute's classroom"></img></p>


<p>Trainings they offer are often longer (3 months on) allowing you to get over your initial frustrations of adjusting to the climate and stomach bugs and dive into Indian philosophy - both intellectually and experientially. Yoga for them is not about physical postures and you probably won’t learn much anatomy there or how to run your yoga business back home. But if you do stay open and allow yourself to experience something new without judgement, you might set a foundation to growing into a completely different you. At least for me, this was the single most valuable thing from studying yoga in India.</p>

<h3>They always say the Institute was there before the airport and will stay, as the city around it keeps growing and changing.</h3>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/the-garden.jpg" alt="The YOga Institute's modest but peaceful garden"></img></p>


<p>I would warmly recommend the institute where I studied - <a href="http://theyogainstitute.org/">The Yoga Institute in Santacruz East</a>, the busy Mumbai neighbourhood with shouting street vendors and shattering noise of planes landing and taking off from the nearby airport. They always say the Institute was there before the airport and will stay, as the city around it keeps growing and changing. And it really does, maintaining an oasis of peace and simple, traditional values in the midst of all the hustle and bustle of Mumbai. The Institute was established in 1918 by their grandfather Shri Yogendra, disciple of Paramahamsa Madhavdasji. Its work is dedicated mainly to “householders”, trying to educate and bring together local community around yogic lifestyle and yoga philosophy applied to everyday life.</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/children-yoga.jpg" alt="children class at the institute"></img></p>


<p>Also, another Institute I always recommend is the yogic hospital and research centre <a href="http://kdham.com/">Kaivalyadham</a> in Lonavla, the mountain area somewhere in between Mumbai and Pune. It’s interesting that they trace their teaching back to the same guru (<a href="http://www.yogadhama.com/ecole-yoga/?The-KAIVALYADHAMA-Centre&amp;lang=en">Madhavdasji</a>). Kaivalyadham has recently tried to modernise their approach, starting to offer online courses, but I think the greatest value you can get from there would be to go and spend some time living at the Institute, fully immersed into their value system and modest way of life.</p>

<h3>Only for male Indian residents?</h3>

<p>There is probably a whole lot more of similar places to discover. Unfortunately some of them offer their courses only in Hindi or only to male Indian residents. Anyway, you should definitely explore what there is, do a nice research before you choose where to go and maybe try to get in touch with at least one person who studied there, just to help you set expectations.</p>

<p>Good luck!</p>

<p>P.S. All the photos here were taken in Mumbai during the summer and autumn 2012 that I spent studying at The Yoga Institute in Santacruz East.</p>

<p>This post was also published on <a href="https://medium.com/@zzuuu/why-go-to-india-to-study-yoga-d88e2ea8c750">Medium</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[So how do I meditate?]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2015/02/12/so-how-do-i-meditate/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-12T22:26:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2015/02/12/so-how-do-i-meditate</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Once the motivation is there, you really don’t need much to start your meditation practice, just a couple of minutes every day when you won’t be distracted and a comfortable position in which the body won’t complain.</p>

<p>Maybe the easiest type of meditation to start with would be mindfulness meditation, which is basically sitting still and watching your breath for a couple of moments.</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/blur-meditation.jpg" alt="a person meditating"></img></p>


<h3>Pick time and place for your practice</h3>

<p>You might choose to dedicate a special corner of your home to meditation, trying to associate this place with the attitude of quietude and introspection. However, once you get comfortable with the technique you can meditate anywhere else too - on the public transport commuting to work, sitting on a park bench (my favourite one in summer) or in the office when you want to clear your mind in between meetings.</p>

<p>Meditation itself doesn’t require any special time, but it&#8217;s easier to develop a habit if you practise always at the same time, even for only 10 minutes. You can gradually extend the time to 15, 20 and 30 min a day. But try to sit every day to meditate, even for just 5 minutes on really busy days. Remember the old Roman saying <em>nulla dies sine linea</em> - no day without drawing at least a line, even sitting still for just a couple of minutes counts!</p>

<p>I personally find it the easiest to meditate straight after waking up in the morning, when the mind is still in the quitter, night mode, and before jumping on the to-do-list for the day. However, any other time should be fine too, as long as you stick to it. You can tie your practice to a certain time or an activity (something like: straight after brushing teeth in the evening), which both help to condition the mind to be “in the mood” for the practice.</p>

<p>Oh, and it’s quite useful, especially in the beginning, to set the timer for ending the practice. Pick some gentle, unobtrusive sound if you can, so your heart doesn’t skip the beat when woken up from the silence.</p>

<h3>Choose the right position</h3>

<p>It&#8217;s really important to find a comfortable position, so you can maintain stillness without worrying too much about the body. However you shouldn&#8217;t be as comfortable as to fall asleep. Meditation is not the same as relaxation. In relaxation we just release the mind, allow it to relax with the body. In meditation the mind stays alert maintaining a sort of relaxed focus. So, find a position which is steady and comfortable for the body, yet allowing you to stay awake and alert.</p>

<p>If you are a beginner, you can simply sit on a hard chair with your back supported (to avoid slouching) and feet touching the floor. If you want you can also sit cross-legged on the floor with the back upright. If the hips feel a bit tight and the lower back is rounding it might be a good idea to sit on a cushion or two. Once the knees are lower than the hips and you don&#8217;t need to constantly fight the gravity as it pulls the knees towards the floor, you might find the cross-legged position really comfortable. You can also kneel, sitting on a couple of cushions with a blanket under the knees or find any another sustainable upright position. I really wouldn&#8217;t recommend lying down, it would be just too easy to fall asleep.</p>

<p>So you’ve found a comfortable position and settled and we can start.</p>

<h3>1. Become aware of your surroundings</h3>

<p>Take a moment to take in everything that your senses are bringing from your environment at this very moment.</p>

<p>You might even keep your eyes open to start with. We are generally very visual beings and it’s probably what you see that will attract your attention first. So let it be. Eyes relaxed, nice soft gaze forward. Take a moment to notice everything in your field of vision without getting involved into thinking about it.</p>

<p>And now we can gently close the eyes, letting the rest of the senses get their spotlight too. Notice any sounds from the outside and inside the room and even the sounds of your own body, breath, digestion, heartbeat. Notice the weight of the body on the floor, the sensation of touch and then all the other information coming from the senses - heat or cold, any smells or a lingering taste in the mouth.</p>

<p>So this is what surrounds you at this very moment. And now we can try to go deeper, looking inwards.</p>

<h3>2. Check in with the body</h3>

<p>Take a moment to become aware how your body is feeling right now. The easiest way to do this is to do a quick “scan”, moving the mind slowly from head to toe as if scanning through. Take a moment to notice how each body part feels as if touching it in your thoughts. At the beginning it might be difficult to do it without an actual movement. So do wiggle your toes if you need to. Every next time it will be easier to just think of a body part and feel it as if being touched, it&#8217;s just a matter of practice.</p>

<p>Try not to stay too long at any body part, whatever you find there. The whole body scan doesn’t need to last more than 20-30 seconds, just gently move awareness through without getting into thinking and analysing what you find. If the mind gets distracted, no worries, gently bring it back to which ever part of the body you last remember and continue from there.</p>

<p>And now we are ready to dive deper in.</p>

<h3>3. Find the breath</h3>

<p>Take a moment to listen to your breath as it is. Observe how the body is breathing right now, without interfering in any way. Notice the depth and quality and maybe any tightness in the breath. How does it feel like to inhale? How does the exhalation feel like? Notice the little pause after the inhalation as the breath gently turns to flow out of the body and the moment of rest after the exhalation, before you take a new breath in. Notice how each breath is slightly different, yet following the same rhythm. Allow yourself to stay still and just watch with curiosity as if observing someone else&#8217;s breathing. Simply let each breath happen.</p>

<h3>4. Stay with the breath</h3>

<p>And now the main trick - stay focused on the breath, as everything else keeps moving and changing. Just let the mind rest on the rhythm of your breathing as it is - right now, at this very moment. This could be a bit difficult in the beginning, so you might prefer to count the breaths. You can count both inhalations and exhalations, so none of them passes unnoticed. This is a great focus exercise and sooner than you think you will find that you can keep the mind on each breath even without counting.</p>

<p>As you stay still watching the breath, let the mind unfold thoughts but try to not get involved. Just step back and watch them as if being projected on a screen. Sometimes these will be your to-do-lists creeping in, thousands of things that you need to finish and problems that need to be solved. Or maybe sometimes you can have memories coming up, people, places and emotions. Don’t judge them, don’t try to stop them. No effort at all. Just let them happen, staying open as they roll through you and pass away. If the mind runs away be patient and bring it gently back to the rhythm of the breath.</p>

<p>Stay with the breath. And eventually the mind gets tired of thinking and just eases into the rhythm of your breathing. And sometimes it feels like the warm comforting silence has become louder than your thoughts, making them sound like soothing background noise. Just let the mind rest, letting go of any effort. Stay still and watch thoughs as they simply roll through and disolve into silence.</p>

<h3>5.  Release the focus</h3>

<p>As we are approaching the very end of the meditation, take a moment to release any focus, even on the breath. For some 10-15 seconds let the mind do whatever it wants to do. Allow the mind to be completely free - to think, if it feels like thinking, or simply relax into the silence.</p>

<p>As the timer starts gently waking you up, take a moment to become aware of the body again and reconnect with your immediate surroundings. Notice all the sensations coming from the body, your weight on the floor, sounds, smells, tastes. And finally, when you feel ready, open your eyes.</p>

<p>So, this was all.</p>

<p>There are also a few really nice web and mobile apps that can help you start and stick to your practice, especially if you like to have some guidance at the beginning. Check out <a href="https://www.headspace.com/">Headspace</a> or <a href="http://buddhify.com/">Buddhify</a> for example. They have some really nice ideas for meditations on the go too, just pop in your earphones and you can meditate anywhere.</p>

<p>And now the trick is to keep practising. Remember, <em>nulla dies sine linea</em>! ;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Eccentric Muscle Action - Stengthening and Lengthening]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2015/01/13/eccentric-muscle-action-yoga-and-high-intensity-interval-training/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-13T16:22:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2015/01/13/eccentric-muscle-action-yoga-and-high-intensity-interval-training</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of days ago I read an article in Wired about the <a href="http://www.chhp.com/human-performance-science">Centre for Health and Human Performance (CHHP)</a> and their newest work with high intensity interval training. CHHP is a London based clinic and research centre that has been working with some of the world’s top athletes. They use asymmetric loading of muscles varying between concentric action (shortening of muscles to bear effort typical for the &#8220;classical&#8221; fitness) and eccentric action (strengthening + lengthening) in order to decrease body fat while increasing muscle mass.</p>

<p>I find it interesting that newer research in fitness puts more accent on eccentric loading of muscles, typical for yoga. This is the action of keeping a sustained contraction of a muscle while &#8220;relaxing into the effort&#8221; of keeping the pose, so the muscle can steadily lengthen at the same time. And this is the very thing that makes (the physical part of) yoga so special and so much more than  simply stretching or getting a good workout.</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/perfect-side-angle.jpg" alt="side angle pose"></img></p>


<p><a href="http://www.doyoga.com/">Doug Keller</a> beautifully explains the concept of eccentric muscle work in yoga in his groundbreaking set of books Yoga As Therapy. Looking into the structure of muscles, they each consist of a bundle of fibers, encapsulated within fascial wraps. The fibers themselves are made of long protein cords organised in rows. Such structure allows the muscles to shorten without actually having to shorten themselves. It’s just the fibers gliding into each other, similarly to two old-school shaving brushes. If you push the brushes into each other the bristles won’t shorten or contract but just slide into one another, merging into one. This way we can understand how the muscle doesn’t actually loose it’s flexibility as it contracts, it can still lengthen and this is what happens during the eccentric contraction.</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/brushes.jpeg" alt="two shaving brushes"></img></p>


<p>Intrestingly, this is a type of contraction that is common to different types of skeletal muscles that inherently work differently. According to one of the most widely accepted categorisations of muscles set fort by <a href="http://www.jandaapproach.com/about/">Vladimir Janda</a> in 1970-es, the skeletal muscles are either: postural - that maintain the contraction / resistance to hold the bones in place, or phasic - that contract when needed in order to move the bones.</p>

<p>These two don’t just work differently, they are fuelled by a different substance too. The postural muslcles are fueled by oxygen and as such are slow to fatigue and can work continuously without us even thinking about them. This is how we are supposed to maintain out posture against the gravity without getting tired.</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/posture.jpg" alt="postural muscles"></img></p>


<p>On the other hand, the phasic muscles are powered by blood sugar or glucose and need constant energy input to be able to work. They are generally the ones who do the &#8220;heavy lifting&#8221; and more powerful than the postural ones, but fatigue much quicker.</p>

<p>The postural and phasic muscles work together and balance each other’s work. As we move the phasic muscles get consciously activated to get us moving while the postural muscles support their action by providing resistance that keeps the body together and maintains our posture against gravity.</p>

<p>The phasic muscles tend to weaken through lack of use or overuse, due to bad postural habits for example - funnily enough, undoing some of our hard work of developing and strengthening we did as babies to be able to learn to walk. On the contrary, postural muscles have tendency to shorten and tighten over time, more or less depending on how we use the body. And these two phenomenons come in pairs for specific muscles - for example, weak abdominals come in pair with tight psoas. For this reason Keller is writing a lot about the need to address muscles in pairs. In order to strengthen weak muscles we need to release the tight postural muscles that balance them.</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/drawing.jpg" alt="drawing of a figure with arms stretching overhead"></img></p>


<p>Eccentric muscle action allows us to do both at the same time - strengthening while lengthening and both phasic and postural muscles are able to work eccentrically, just with a little bit of practice. And eventually we can release the muscles lengthwise as we activate them, even the postural ones, which usually work without us worrying much about them.</p>

<p>Learning to consciously activate the postural muscles in yoga together with the phasic ones, allowing them to release and lengthen as we contract and lengthen the phasic muscles, the pose grows almost effortless. For example, with a bit of practice you can keep your hands up in the air as the spine lengthens, using almost no effort of the arms as the postural muscles along the spine keep the body in the pose and being able to “relax upwards&#8221;. And this is how yoga practice creates the feeling of length and spaciousness in the body.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[About Meditation]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2014/05/07/about-meditation-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-07T19:30:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2014/05/07/about-meditation-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Meditation is not just an Eastern esoteric practice. In one form or another and under different names it has been around for centuries in both East and West. It has been practised by monks, mystics and intellectuals alike - from St. Thomas Aquinas to Nikola Tesla and Sherlock Holmes who liked to simply sit down and <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/16/opinion/sunday/the-power-of-concentration.html?smid=tw-share&amp;_r=0">&#8220;throw his brain out of action&#8221;</a> before solving any difficult case.</p>

<p>The word meditation itself can mean different things for different people - focusing on the breath, mantra, a sound, an object or an area of the body, keeping the eyes closed or open. But what is it that all these different techniques have in common? It&#8217;s bringing together focus and relaxation (creating a sort of a &#8220;relaxed focus&#8221;). Being truly present, but not &#8220;eaten up&#8221; by the experience. Just watching.</p>

<p>We are so much used to reacting to whatever happens around us. But what if we just stop for a moment and listen instead - staying still as everything keeps moving and changing, around and within us alike? What if we simply step back, stop swimming in our thoughts and just stand on the river bank for a moment watching as the water flows by? Could this be a path to wisdom?</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/silence_over_the_water_1.jpg" alt="a man meditating by the lake"></img></p>


<p>Photo credits: <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/cwithe/4820792641/in/photostream/">#3 Dao by Mitja Kobal</a></p>

<p>Do you know that the physical postures most of us think of when saying &#8220;yoga&#8221; today were initially just an introduction into meditation? According to Classical yoga, the asanas were intended only for making the body strong and steady enough to be able to spend longer time meditating. The breathing practices were similarly used to enhance health and reach deeper levels of focus. According to Patanjali, the compiler of <a href="http://www.athayog.me.uk/sutra_ch1n.html">Yoga Sutras</a> somewhere around 400 CE, yoga itself is stilling the restless mind. Through a process of moral, physical and mental discipline we try to purify the mind so it can become like clear water that reflects universal wisdom.</p>

<p>The motives for meditating in the contemporary society are much different than in the times of Patanjali. Instead of searching for wisdom we are more after the therapeutic benefits of meditation. The modern meditator is looking for a way to fight stress and rest from the chronic information overload. And the good thing is that it actually works! Taking a step back and looking at our worries with detachment we suddenly feel like Alice in Wonderland, who realised that the Queen of Hearts and whole her army are just a stack of harmless playing cards.</p>

<p>There is a growing body of scientific research about benefits of different meditation techniques. <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3004979/">One of the studies</a> for example, shows that regular practice of simple mindfulness meditation can cause structural changes in grey matter of the brain, especially in the areas in charge for learning and memory processes, emotion regulation and the perception of self. If you want to find out more, there is a nice article I recently found on <a href="http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/use-your-mind-change-your-brain/201305/is-your-brain-meditation">psychologytoday.com</a> that explains in plain language what happens with the brain &#8220;on meditation&#8221;, check it out.</p>

<p>At the end of the day, it doesn&#8217;t even matter what your motivation to start practising meditation is. The beautiful thing is that with time and patience your practice will grow out of any motive and become a purpose to itself, gently transforming you on its way in a calmer, more compassionate and more balanced person.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Healthy Breakfast Idea - Chocolate Kale Smoothie]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2014/02/14/a-healthy-breakfast-idea-chocolate-kale-smoothie/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-14T16:33:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2014/02/14/a-healthy-breakfast-idea-chocolate-kale-smoothie</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What if we add a quirky chocolate twist to a healthy green kale smoothie? Kale and chocolate? Sounds a bit unusual&#8230; But it turned out to be delicious!</p>

<p>Kale is such a versatile smoothie ingredient, with a taste that can beautifully blend into any fruit and on top of it, has more iron than beef and more calcium than milk. Just don&#8217;t forget removing stalks, because they taste quite bitter. So yes, this morning i tried to experiment combining kale with cacao, fresh pears and almonds and it worked brilliantly. Ended up with such a rich fruity taste!</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/chocolate-kale-smoothie.jpg" alt="chocolate kale smoothie photo"></img></p>


<p>If you would be up for trying this healthy chocolate breakfast drink here is the recipe:</p>

<h3>Ingredients:</h3>

<ul>
<li>3 big leaves of kale ( i used curly cale, but i guess any other type would work just fine)</li>
<li>2 medium pears, peeled and cleaned of seeds</li>
<li>1 banana</li>
<li>1 handful of almonds</li>
<li>1 table spoon of chia seeds</li>
<li>1 table spoon of raw non-refined coconut oil</li>
<li>1 big glass of almond milk</li>
<li>2 table spoons of organic cacao powder</li>
<li>A little bit of honey (optional)</li>
</ul>


<h3>Preparation:</h3>

<p>Removing the stalks place the kale leaves in the blender, add almonds, chia seeds, a splash of almond milk and the coconut oil and blend them on the lowest speed until all is broken into small pieces. I add chia seeds in pretty much every smoothie for their high nutritional value, but you can skip them if you don&#8217;t have any.</p>

<p>Add the banana and the pears and blend them in, gradually increasing the speed.</p>

<p>Finally, add the cacao, stir it in and adding the remaining almond milk blend everything together on highest speed until smooth. If you want to have slightly crunchier texture (as I do) you can throw in some of the almonds now too and blend them shortly with the rest of the mixture.</p>

<p>The smoothie already has a very rich, fresh and slightly nutty flavour, but If you would like it sweeter, don&#8217;t feel guilty to blend in a little bit of honey. Pour it in glasses, decorate with a tiny piece of crumbled dark chocolate and enjoy your delicious healthy treat!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Warrior Mum]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2013/09/05/warrior-mum/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-05T16:44:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2013/09/05/warrior-mum</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve been really enjoying teaching pregnancy yoga during my own pregnancy – sharing the practice with my lovely group of mums-to-be, going together through all the ups and downs of this fragile and powerful period of our lives and being inspired by each other. However, it gets a bit inconvenient when you become the most pregnant of all the students. Running around and trying to help everyone out with slight modifications of postures becomes quite a challenge. So, entering my 39th week, I&#8217;ve decided to start the maternity leave and resume teaching in November.</p>

<p>The last class for this season was dedicated to a theme I wanted to focus on for quite some time - Warrior Mum.</p>

<p>I love the warrior poses, with their strong grounded feet, the open heart and arms expanding powerfully up or to the sides. According to yoga every physical posture (asana) cultivates a certain attitude if performed regularly and with dedication, so flexibility of the body becomes flexibility of the mind. The warrior poses in this sense cultivate courage and open-heartedness, floating over the strong feet with wide open arms and giving hands. A beautiful metaphor for motherhood!</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/DancingWarrior.jpg" alt="Dancing Warrior asana"></img></p>


<p>Recently I came upon an interesting <a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/amy_cuddy_your_body_language_shapes_who_you_are.html">TED talk by Amy Cuddy</a>, a social psychologist from Harvard who doesn&#8217;t have to do anything with yoga, but thinks that bodily postures we regularly assume shape the way we feel about ourselves and others. So, the poses of power, as she calls them, with legs comfortably apart and chest proudly forward, not only leave that impression on others, but can also boost our confidence and encourage us to develop such qualities in ourselves. Classical warrior would be a great example of a power pose in this sense.</p>

<p>The physical part of the class was focussed on energising flowing sequences based on and around the warrior poses. We started gradually preparing the body through loosening the spine, opening the hips and chest and strengthening the legs for a firmer grip in these powerful standing poses. I also found it useful to finish the class with more restorative poses releasing the tension in the lower back and hips.</p>

<p>Here are the little stick-men I drew planning this class:</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/PregnancyYogaClass22-Warrior_Mum_1.jpg" alt="Class plan page 1"></img></p>




<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/PregnancyYogaClass22-Warrior_Mum_2.jpg" alt="Class plan page 2"></img></p>




<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/PregnancyYogaClass22-Warrior_Mum_3.jpg" alt="Class plan page 3"></img></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Belly Dance Inspired Yoga]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2013/08/26/belly-dance-inspired-yoga/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-26T20:04:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2013/08/26/belly-dance-inspired-yoga</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Did you know that in many parts of the world they have special dances for pregnancy and birth, celebrating fertility, roundness and ripeness of the female body in pregnancy? This is how the oriental belly dance was &#8220;invented&#8221;. It was a dance of pregnancy, dedicated to the moon as the feminine element. Heavily pregnant women would get together with their female cousins and just dance. Men would not even be allowed in there, it was a &#8220;women&#8217;s thing&#8221;. The soft circular and spiral movements of the belly and the whole body were used to keep the woman healthy and strong and get the baby in the optimal position for birth. They would give birth dancing, gently nudging the baby down the birth canal in soft round motions.</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/belly_dance_logo_by_contrapposto.jpg" alt="Belly dancer painting"></img></p>


<p>Photo credits: <a href="http://contrapposto.deviantart.com/art/Belly-Dance-Logo-69814644">Contrapposto</a></p>

<p>Inspired by the lovely lady at my recent <a href="http://www.activebirthcentre.com/">Active Birth workshop</a> who told me about the secret of belly dancing, I prepared a pregnancy yoga class based on oriental belly dance. The moves of belly dance are perfect for releasing tension in the hips, opening and energising the pelvic area and strengthening deep abdominal muscles. It was quite fun to let the hips roll experimenting with plenty of gentle round movements and I&#8217;m sure the little ones loved it too.</p>

<p>Researching and planning the class I&#8217;ve found out that there is already a couple of teachers, though mostly in the US and Australia who try to bring together yoga and belly dance. An interesting example is Australian based Lebanese-Palestinian <a href="http://www.bellydanceforbirth.com/flex/about_maha/47/1">Maha Al Musa</a>, a dancer, doula, writer and human rights activist, who gave birth to her last child at the age of 46 in her own home - belly dancing :) Here is one of her videos explaining the basic circular movement in belly dance.</p>

<iframe src="http://yogawithivana.com//www.youtube.com/embed/1kUkJ8_fm8w" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>Another lady who really knows how to spin her hips in the right way is Las Vegas based Amira, a belly dancer who released a DVD called <a href="http://www.pregnantbellydance.com/">Belly Dance and Yoga for Pregnancy</a>. The yoga part is very very basic and transitions between the poses sometimes quite rough, but the belly dancing part is awesome! It took me a while to decipher some of the hip loops. Later I realised that it&#8217;s better to just let the hips get the movement before the mind.</p>

<p>Belly dance is not really an easy thing. In order to master it you need to learn how to move each segment of your body separately. I found it crazy how, for example, they can dance with the chest only while keeping the rest of the body still. So, only the part from the diaphragm to the neck moves, while the shoulders stay where they are. Or maybe moving just one hip in very tight circles&#8230; Huh, I guess these things are a bit out of reach for most of us in the West, used to use our hips in a bit&#8230;hm&#8230; more politically correct way.</p>

<p>Anyway, here are some of the little drawings I made during my research for the class, trying to understand the loops of hips drawing diagrams (oh, so Western from me).</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/BellyDanceResearch_HorizontalMoves.jpg" alt="Class research page 1"></img></p>




<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/BellyDanceResearch_UpperBodyMoves.jpg" alt="Class research page 2"></img></p>


<p>And here is the belly dance inspired yoga class we had (yeah, some more stick men :)</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/PregnancyYogaClass21-Belly_Dance_1.jpg" alt="Class plan page 1"></img></p>




<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/PregnancyYogaClass21-Belly_Dance_2.jpg" alt="Class plan page 2"></img></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Diary of Blooming]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2013/08/15/the-diary-of-blooming-thursday-15-august-2013/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-15T08:36:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2013/08/15/the-diary-of-blooming-thursday-15-august-2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The morning started with a moment of deep wordless gratitude, sitting in the living room under the pots of blooming flowers. Sitting quietly on the floor while sun gently shines through my eyelids. The room full of bright coloured cushions and soft things. A white cuddly toy cat patiently waiting for the tiny hand to touch and squeeze its soft cotton tail.</p>

<p>The tiny one is awake, cosily wriggling in his safe little house, gently pushing his round little bum through the skin of my upper belly. I sing for him softly and gently cuddle the little knee as it moves trough my skin.</p>

<p>Dain came early from work. Our little ritual of kissing for long time on the door, he with his cycling helmet on. Making a big colourful salad together and going for a walk under trees in Hackney Downs. The fragile young oak tree that we were watering is getting better now. Slowly growing fresh green leaves, whole bunches of them, some straight from its gentle trunk. I feel like everything is growing and blooming around and inside me, such a magical feeling.</p>

<p>I feel so grateful for living this life as it is, maybe not perfect, maybe I could have achieved more (my mum would certainly say so) but I&#8217;m happy following my path. Learning and growing. Giving and sharing. Letting the nature unfold the miracle of life through my body. Slowly spreading my branches and watching the buds emerging from the leaves and opening very slowly. Gentle flowers gradually turning into little green fruits that under the soft touch of sunshine slowly become redder, plumper and juicier, until the stems slowly break, obeying to the roundness and ripeness of this new life and setting it free.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Strength and Softness]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2013/08/11/strength-and-softness/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-11T13:44:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2013/08/11/strength-and-softness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The theme for this week&#8217;s pregnancy yoga class was feminine strength and softness and childbirth as a perfect balance of the two.</p>

<p>For me personally, one of the most powerful motives from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yoga_Sutras_of_Patanjali">Yoga Sutras</a> is bringing together the opposites of constant efforts (abhyasa) and detachment (vayragya), finding a balance between being strong and letting go. In yoga we strive to find a way to reconcile these seemingly conflicting qualities so they could become one – understanding that a relaxed body is a strong body and a relaxed mind is a strong mind.</p>

<p>Applied to the birth, this means that strong muscles and a fit body are not enough to prepare you to go through the challenge of opening your body for the new life to emerge. Especially in the last part of pregnancy it&#8217;s all about melting and softening, learning how to relax and go inwards, taking the mind out of the way of the body, allowing the cervix to soften and open. Besides cultivating the strength in ourselves we need to learn how to embrace our weakness too. Instead of fighting against pain you need to be able to dive into it, relax into it, letting go of any inhibitions, giving up your ego in hands of a force much more powerful than your own will – the force of nature.</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/overexposed.jpg" alt="Shadow play asana"></img></p>


<p>Photo credits: <a href="http://illuminate.uwenna.com/post/27628467620/shadow-play-asana">uwenna</a></p>

<p>Finding inspiration somewhere in between Yoga Sutras, Vinyasa Flow, Hypnobirthing relaxation techniques and Tantric visualisations, think I finally managed to strike the fragile balance between a restorative and enough physically challenging class to keep all my mums-to-be happy.</p>

<p>Since I have a very mixed group of expectant mums in different stages of pregnancy, with very different levels of previous experience with yoga, I&#8217;ve been experimenting with various ways to make the class suitable for each of them. So far I had the best experience with combining active segments with frequent short relaxation, either in one of the restorative poses (e.g. <a href="http://www.yogajournal.com/poses/475">child pose</a> and its variations), either in a form of active relaxation through slow and relaxing movements. In this class I&#8217;ve tried to go a step further and make the active segments shorter but more intense, interlacing them with guided relaxation, visualisations and deepening techniques, trying to reach a very deep level of relaxation in a short time. And it worked perfectly! All the mums-to-be were able to follow the class without any strain.</p>

<p>Here are some drawings I made planning the class:</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/PregnancyYoga19-Strength_Softness_1.jpg" alt="Class plan 1"></img></p>




<p class="centeredimage"><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/PregnancyYoga19-Strength_Softness_2.jpg" alt="Class plan 2"></img></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Soap Bubble That Would Last Forever]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2013/07/01/a-bubble-of-magic/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-01T12:37:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2013/07/01/a-bubble-of-magic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a kid I was always fascinated with soap bubbles. I would spend time connecting them and turning into triple, quadruple, octuple, &#8220;recycling&#8221; the bubbles and trying to extend their life. I dreamt of a soap bubble that would last forever. But what would be the point? - most people would say. There is nothing really interesting in soap. The beauty of a soap bubble lies in its fragility, in its impermanence. Each bubble is new and special, fluttering in front of your eyes, impossible to grasp and that is exactly what is fun about them.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s a strange nature of the human mind. We stop noticing beauty in things that last, that are simply there. It&#8217;s only new that manages to tickle our curiosity and trap our short attention span used to restlessly click between links in the browser or between TV channels. We always look for new, and turn it into old as soon as we reach it. And this is what the whole consumer mentality is all about too - chasing soap bubbles that disappear as we touch them, running after a butterfly that turns into a catterpilar as soon as it lands on your palm.</p>

<p>Well, it&#8217;s not the fault of the butterfly, it&#8217;s our hand that breaks the magic, it&#8217;s our eye that doesn&#8217;t see it as such anymore. Nothing in the world is static, everything keeps changing and every moment is new and unique. It&#8217;s just that we get stuck in our own idea about things and people that surround us and this overshadows their real nature. We don&#8217;t see them as they are, we see our opinions about them, memories, judgements and prejudices. Labeling the things around us we stop finding excitement in them, always chasing the &#8220;new&#8221; and untouched.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropbox.com/u/3886907/miau/the%20bubble%20by%20lou%20bernstein.jpg" alt="Bubbles" /></p>

<p>Isn&#8217;t it ironic that it usually takes an accident or a terminal illness to be able to stop, take a deep breath and check what is really important in your life? To find beauty in things that were there all the time but you just didn&#8217;t notice them anymore&#8230;</p>

<p>There is an ancient practice developed by Jain monks which I find quite interesting. Every evening you wrap the day up by sitting down and closing your eyes, letting the day unfold in your mind frame by frame, like on a movie screen. Simply watching everything that happened without analysing it, you scan slowly through your day, from the moment of waking up all the way to the moment when you sat down and closed your eyes. And with time you not only improve your memory, but gain the ability to detach and experience your life from the aspect of an impartial witness. You develop the habit of living in the present moment as it happens, seeing the life as a succession of moments instead of continuity. And you realise how everything is changing, how precious and unique each moment is, new and unrepeatable.</p>

<p>So yes, I do believe it&#8217;s just a matter of practice - escaping from the established perception patterns and being open to see things as new in each new moment that unfolds. Developing appreciation for the world around us and the ability to notice beauty in &#8220;ordinary&#8221; things, we overcome the need for short-term thrills. Every moment of your life becomes a new and irreproducible experience, reflected in billions of soup bubbles dispersing light always in a new way.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[From Radish to Motherhood as a Dharma]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2013/05/22/from-radish-to-motherhood-as-a-dharma/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-22T23:20:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2013/05/22/from-radish-to-motherhood-as-a-dharma</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>During my last year&#8217;s stay at The Yoga Institute Santacruz in Mumbai I was amongst other trained in pregnancy yoga. This included assisting and teaching in both antenatal and postnatal camps / weekend workshops that the Institute held for local women. The camps reflected a holistic approach to yoga and pregnancy focused on learning about yogic philosophy and the way of life, from diet and positive thinking to different traditional Hatha yoga techniques adapted to pregnancy.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s beautiful how Hindu people see pregnancy and motherhood as a manifestation of the female divine force in each woman. The life-giving role is empowering women and raising them to the god-like level in this society which is still quite discriminative towards the &#8220;weaker sex&#8221;. From the Hindu perspective, becoming a mother awakens and cultivates the qualities of the universal mother in every woman - strength, selflessness and unconditional love. So a real mother is not only the mother of her baby but mother to every child, realising motherhood as a part of her dharma, her innate purpose.</p>

<p>India made me recognise and embrace my own, back then quite shy, mother instinct. After coming back home I felt I was ready&#8230; if it&#8217;s possible to ever be. The right time you don&#8217;t wait for, you make it, I guess. &#8220;Let&#8217;s make a tiny creature!&#8221; - I whispered to Dain. &#8220;Let&#8217;s!&#8221; - he answers, being always open to support me in all the crazy ideas. And everything happened so quickly. A couple of weeks later here we are, Dain and me in a supermarket manically searching for radish, my first craving.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/3886907/miau/yoga-bump.jpg" alt="Yoga with a bump" /></p>

<p>Becoming a mum-to-be gave me a chance to deepen and ground everything I&#8217;ve learnt about pregnancy yoga before, this time on my own changing body. I kept practising yoga every day since the first day of my pregnancy, slowing down and doing more relaxation during the bad days and being more active during the good days. It helped me stay calm and bright thought the period of nausea and strange pains and strong and energised afterwards. I&#8217;m really grateful that everything has been going well so far and I&#8217;m going through my pregnancy cheerful and full of energy. I try to express this gratitude through sharing my passion and this bit of knowledge and experience with other mums-to-be who might be going through similar things.</p>

<p>Since coming back from India I&#8217;ve been learning about some contemporary approaches to yoga in pregnancy as well. I am really passionate about <a href="http://www.bellybelly.com.au/birth/active-birth">Active Birth</a> movement and work of <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/health-17589544">Janet Balaskas</a>, the founder of the <a href="http://www.activebirthcentre.com/">Active Birth Centre</a>. Also I find <a href="http://www.hypnobirthing.co.uk/">hypnobirthing (the Mongan method)</a> quite interesting, as well as <a href="http://www.birthlight.com/">Birthlight</a> pregnancy yoga based on work of <a href="http://www.ice.cam.ac.uk/components/tutors/?view=tutor&amp;id=2071&amp;cid=4223">Francoise Barbira Freedman</a>, a medical anthropologist from Cambridge inspired by energetic but gentle mothering of tribal women from Peruvian Amazon. All these have tremendously influenced my pregnancy yoga classes and my own everyday yoga practice.</p>

<p>After some 300 years of development of modern obstetrics and dominance of medically imposed recumbent positions for labour, forceps, epidurals and unnecessary cesarians, luckily there are now stronger and stronger voices speaking up for the innate right of women as instinctive birth-givers. The right of a mother to give birth to her child changing positions guided by her instincts, in full control of her birthing experience, is more and more recognised as important for health of both mother and the child and for development of a healthy bonding between them. I am so grateful to be living in a country where alternative approaches to childbirth have been slowly melting into the mainstream. If everything goes right, Vuk is going to be a water baby, gently swimming from water into the water, before being ready to take his first breath of the chilly London air.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Yoga Story]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2012/02/18/my-yoga-story/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-18T12:33:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2012/02/18/my-yoga-story</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Trying to describe the difference yoga has made in my life, I would compare it with the sun behind and out of clouds. Everything is still standing where it used to be, but painted in brighter, more vibrant colours, feeling fuller, richer and more real. Yoga brought together so many different puzzle pieces that I was collecting for years, encompassing values that I was unknowingly developing throughout my life. It felt like coming home - everything gently clicked into its place.</p>

<h3>Silence</h3>

<p>I have been always fascinated with sound - growing up surrounded with music, my dad was teaching guitar. It was through music that I learnt to make my mind clear of thoughts and just be, diving into every sound separately, letting them make me spontaneously smile. Through sound I discovered my fascination with silence, rich textures composed of different little noises blending together. I often remember places by their silence. I love silence of rooftops, for example, with faraway traffic sounds softly melting into children laughter and sound of cutlery from a nearby restaurant. I&#8217;ve learnt to quieten my mind and listen, gently pushing away any thought and letting the soothing mixture of background noises fill every corner of my mind.</p>

<h3>Movement</h3>

<p>My roller skates used to be my yoga mat, it was an over 10 year long passion. I used to skate every day, just putting my skates on and sailing the streets, switching the mind off and just melting into the long smooth movements, feeling the wheels caressing the asphalt as if they were my own soles. It was the same thing I liked about skiing - the smooth touch of snow under your feet as your skis glide down a sleek mountain side. The grace and lightness of the movement making the mind shut down to the level of a soothing background noise&#8230;</p>

<h3>The Love Story</h3>

<p>I discovered my fascination with yoga quite late, in 2010. But like with every true love, it felt like we always knew each other somehow. Funny, things we are looking for are often already there but we just don’t see them. This is how I met my husband too. We lived in Budapest 3 streets away from each other and we never met. And then years later when I was already living in Amsterdam for years and he in London, we both came to Budapest for a weekend and stumbled upon each other. It was funny to realise that we knew the same people, went to the same concerts and have memories of the same places, but we never met before. Less than 6 months later we got married.</p>

<h3>Home</h3>

<p>I was born in a small town on the River Drina in former Yugoslavia. Since then I moved over 30 times, first to Belgrade, then Budapest, Berlin, Amsterdam, London. Changes became a part of who I was and I kept restlessly moving around, trying to fill an emptiness of not feeling at home by moving again and again. It took me a long time to realise that home is not a place but a feeling - being at ease with the world and who you are.</p>

<h3>Something That Matters</h3>

<p>I spent 9 years of my life studying law and working in a corporate law office. Being a lawyer felt like being on a wrong bus, but warm and cosy enough to prevent me to simply get off. “When you feel fire lighting up within you just run” says one writer from my home country - “you never know when the flame is going to die out and leave you alone in the darkness”. I think I was lucky to recognise the right moment and jump off. So I decided to quit my career in pursue of something that matters. This wasn’t an easy journey, however I never looked back. Yoga was a catalyst and the driving force of my search for that something that matters, but completing the first teacher’s training I realised that yoga IS that something. And this is where my real journey began.</p>

<h3>Sharing</h3>

<p>I did my first yoga teacher training course with the Yoga Federation of Serbia in my home country. It was a 200h training spread over 8 months, based on the holistic approach to yoga and inspired by Bihar school of yoga and Sivananda yoga tradition. I started the training with the idea of using yoga to encourage my husband and me to move a bit more and even without a serious intention to teach other people. However along the way, I discovered that the real beauty lies in sharing. I realised how heart-warming it is to see glowing faces of people coming out of your class, energized and relaxed, how rewarding it is to give and share your knowledge and passion with others.</p>

<p>The journey took me further to India, to the Yoga Institute Santacruz in Maharashtra. The Institute was established in 1918 by Shri Yogendra, disciple of Paramahamsa Madhavdasji and since then run by Yogendra family, preserving traditional values of yoga. I spent last summer and autumn there, studying classical yoga (900 hrs) based on Patanjali’s Sutras and Bhagavad Gita and volunteering as a teacher in health camps and workshops that the Institute regularly held.</p>

<h3>Life-Long Learning</h3>

<p>Spending more time learning yoga, more I&#8217;m aware of its beauty and deepness. Even after years of studying it feels like you&#8217;ve just scraped the surface of its vast amount of knowledge. I&#8217;m just at the beginning of this journey and there is still a long way to go, but I&#8217;m happy to search for it. I believe in life-long learning, being receptive and open to always look at things in a new way. I believe in humbleness, dedication and learning - with mind, heart and gut.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
