<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: raw food | Yoga with Ivana]]></title>
  <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/categories/raw-food/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-09-15T23:25:23+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://yogawithivana.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ivana Miletic Demmel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Healthy Breakfast Idea - Chocolate Kale Smoothie]]></title>
    <link href="http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2014/02/14/a-healthy-breakfast-idea-chocolate-kale-smoothie/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-14T16:33:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://yogawithivana.com/thoughts/2014/02/14/a-healthy-breakfast-idea-chocolate-kale-smoothie</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What if we add a quirky chocolate twist to a healthy green kale smoothie? Kale and chocolate? Sounds a bit unusual... But it turned out to be delicious!</p>

<p>Kale is such a versatile smoothie ingredient, with a taste that can beautifully blend into any fruit and on top of it, has more iron than beef and more calcium than milk. Just don't forget removing stalks, because they taste quite bitter. So yes, this morning i tried to experiment combining kale with cacao, fresh pears and almonds and it worked brilliantly. Ended up with such a rich fruity taste!</p>

<p class="centeredimage"><img src="http://yogawithivana.com/images/chocolate-kale-smoothie.jpg" alt="chocolate kale smoothie photo"></img></p>


<p>If you would be up for trying this healthy chocolate breakfast drink here is the recipe:</p>

<h3>Ingredients:</h3>

<ul>
<li>3 big leaves of kale ( i used curly cale, but i guess any other type would work just fine)</li>
<li>2 medium pears, peeled and cleaned of seeds</li>
<li>1 banana</li>
<li>1 handful of almonds</li>
<li>1 table spoon of chia seeds</li>
<li>1 table spoon of raw non-refined coconut oil</li>
<li>1 big glass of almond milk</li>
<li>2 table spoons of organic cacao powder</li>
<li>A little bit of honey (optional)</li>
</ul>


<h3>Preparation:</h3>

<p>Removing the stalks place the kale leaves in the blender, add almonds, chia seeds, a splash of almond milk and the coconut oil and blend them on the lowest speed until all is broken into small pieces. I add chia seeds in pretty much every smoothie for their high nutritional value, but you can skip them if you don't have any.</p>

<p>Add the banana and the pears and blend them in, gradually increasing the speed.</p>

<p>Finally, add the cacao, stir it in and adding the remaining almond milk blend everything together on highest speed until smooth. If you want to have slightly crunchier texture (as I do) you can throw in some of the almonds now too and blend them shortly with the rest of the mixture.</p>

<p>The smoothie already has a very rich, fresh and slightly nutty flavour, but If you would like it sweeter, don't feel guilty to blend in a little bit of honey. Pour it in glasses, decorate with a tiny piece of crumbled dark chocolate and enjoy your delicious healthy treat!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
